创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在 所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了我们生存的限制
beyond the limits of our existence...
这个空间我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
太阳风 宇宙射线 紫外线辐射
Solar wind, cosmic rays, and UV radiation.
它们都是来自外太空的力量 影响着我们的日常生活
They're forces from outer space that affect our lives every day...
我们大多数人甚至还不知道它
and most of us don't even know it.
从皮肤癌到通讯中断
From skin cancer to lost transmissions...
这些宇宙现象会给我们带来伤害
these cosmic phenomena can cause us harm...
但是它们也会给我们带来绚丽夺目的极光
yet they can also dazzle us with the beauty of an aurora...
和灿烂的流星
and the brilliance of a shooting star.
敬请收看集奇观与危害于一身的
Get ready for the wonders and the dangers...
《宇宙现象》
of "Cosmic Phenomena."
宇宙:宇宙现象
它恢宏壮观
It's just magnificent.
它变幻莫测
It's full of dynamic motion.
我们看到它千变万化
It is changing every time we look at it.
它是你所见到的最大的东西
It's the biggest thing you have ever seen.
它是美轮美奂的景色
It's just a beautiful sight...
好像全然不同于我们所知的一切
kind of completely unlike anything we know.
简直不可思议 空中居然有这样的表现
It's so weird to see the sky behaving in such a fashion.
你看到天上这些闪烁的光辉
You see these flittering lights in the sky...
它们千变万化 绚丽多彩
and they're changing with time in beautiful and wondrous ways.
真是恍若世外
It's really an out-of-this-world experience.
人的一生
Once in everyone's lifetime...
应该去看一回最壮观的景象之一
they should see one of the most spectacular...
魔幻般的光彩表现出大自然的慷慨
psychedelic light shows that nature gives us...
那就是北极光
and that's the aurora borealis.
其名字来自奥罗拉(曙光) 罗马曙光女神
It was named after Aurora, the Roman goddess of dawn...
和希腊北风之神 玻瑞阿斯
and the Greek god of the north wind, Boreas.
在南半球
In the southern hemisphere...
它被称为南极光
it's known as the aurora australis.
它们长期困惑着天文学家
Way before they dazzled astronomers...
极光震撼了第一个在极地见到它的人
auroras amazed the first people who saw them in the polar regions.
惟有古斯堪的纳维亚人
To ancient Scandinavians...
会对这眼花缭乱的展现作出同样惊人的解释
only an equally amazing explanation for the dazzling displays would do.
他们相信天上有一只大狐狸 甩动着尾巴
They believed a giant fox in the sky, swooshing its tail...
导致了北极光的出现
caused the northern lights to appear.
我喜欢这个解释
I like that explanation...
因为它并非不切实际
because it is not that far from the truth.
极光是一种电现象
The aurora is an electric phenomena.
在狐狸甩动尾巴时
And when a fox swooshes its tail around...
你在和静电打交道
you deal with static electricity...
你可能实际上产生了火花 类似极光的现象
and you may actually make sparks and an aurora-like phenomenon.
如果你想知道极光是怎么来的
lf you want to know how an aurora comes about...
就必须从太阳说起
you have to start at the Sun.
太阳
The Sun.
它不光是光源 而且还是能源 大量的能源
It's not only our source of light, but also energy, lots of it.
太阳发出源源不断的带电粒子流
The Sun emits a steady stream of charged particles...
叫做太阳风
known as solar wind...
有时会被日冕物质抛射加剧的宇宙力量
a cosmic force sometimes intensified by a coronal mass ejection.
太阳风会导致大气层上部的辉光
Solar wind can cause some glow in the upper atmosphere...
几乎全年任何时候
nearly any time of the year.
不过 偶尔 太阳会有这些巨大的爆发
But, occasionally, the Sun has these tremendous outbursts.
它们被称为太阳耀斑或日冕物质抛射
They're called solar flares or coronal mass ejections.
于是整个带电粒子流
And then a whole stream of charged particles...
差不多同时奔向地球
comes to the Earth at about the same time...
一大团 一大团
a whole bundle, a whole bunch of them.
那便产生了大量炫丽的极光现象
And that then causes a lot brighter auroral phenomena.
速度高达每秒750英里
Traveling at speeds of up to 750 miles per second...
使得太阳风在两天左右就抵达地球的磁场
it takes solar wind about two days to reach the Earth's magnetic field.
随着带电粒子...
As the energized particles...
沿着磁场流向两极...
stream along the magnetic field towards the poles...
它们激发了地球大气层上部的气体
they excite gases on the Earth's upper atmosphere...
产生出彩光 形成了极光
and produce the colored lights that make up the aurora.
高能粒子轰击大气层上部
When the energetic particles hit the upper atmosphere...
首先遇上氧原子
they first encounter atomic oxygen...
给我们带来红光谱射线
which gives us the red line emission...
绿光谱射线
and the green line emission...
极光中最普遍的射线
the most prevalent emission in aurora.
往下 你会遇上氮分子
Further down, you can encounter molecular nitrogen...
那就给我们 要是极光非常剧烈的话
and that gives us, if the aurora's very intense...
在绿帷幕的底部边缘
at the bottom edge of the green curtain...
有紫色的下摆
a purple lower border.
带电粒子与敏感气体相互作用
Charged particles interacting with excitable gases...
产生出明亮的光彩
to produce bright colors...
极光的活动极像霓虹灯
the aurora functions much like a neon sign.
霓虹灯的原理 如果你取上少许稀有气体
Neon works by-- If you take a little bit of a rare gas...
放入压力极小的管子里
and put it in a tube at very low pressure...
然后你通电 随便从3000V 或4000V
and then you apply anywhere from 3,000 or 4,000 volts...
或者1.5万V 电离气体
to maybe 15,000 volts will ionize the gas...
激发它发出其特有的色彩
and excite it into giving off its characteristic color.
可以用在所有霓虹灯里的气体有氙
The gases that are available for all neon signs are xenon...
纯青色
which is a real pale blue...
氦 这种桃红色
helium, which is a kind of a peach color...
氪 银色
krypton, which is a silver color--
不是行星
it's not a planet--
氩 淡紫色
and argon, which is lavender...
氖 最亮
and neon, which is the brightest...
尤其是在雨夜
especially on a rainy night.
极光 同样 晚上看最
Auroras, too, are best viewed at night...
尤其是极地的冬季
especially during winter in polar regions...
那时的夜晚又长又黑
when the nights are as long as they are dark.
根据太阳活动的规模
Depending on the amount of solar activity...
极光可以持续从几分钟到数日不等
auroras can last from a few minutes to several days...
能见到的不仅是极地附近
and be seen not only near the poles...
而且 罕见的情况下 还有低纬度地区
but also, on rare occasions, at lower latitudes.
就在几年前的2003年
Just a few years ago in 2003...
我们遇上了我们所谓的世纪风暴
we had what we call a century storm...
百年不遇的最大的磁暴
the biggest magnetic storm in a hundred years.
一个大极光随之而来
It was a big aurora associated with that.
华盛顿人看到了极光
People in Washington, D.C. could see the aurora...
地中海地区
in the Mediterranean...
各地通常是见不到极光的
everywhere you don't see aurora very often.
我们所知的最大的一次
And one of the biggest that we know of...
是在19世纪中叶
was in the middle of the 19th century...
产生的极光在夏威夷能见到
that caused aurora that was seen from Hawaii...
以及南太平洋的其他地方
and other places in the South Pacific.
它是我们所知有记载的最大的极光
And it is the biggest aurora on record that we know of.
极光甚至在地球之外也能见到
Auroras can even be seen beyond Earth.
太阳风吹向四面八方
The solar wind goes out in all directions...
一路超过行星
reaching further than the planets.
木星和土星都有巨大的磁场
Jupiter and Saturn have huge magnetic fields...
大于我们的地球
bigger than our own...
那就产生了特大特强的极光
which make for especially large and intense auroras.
但是不管它们是在哪里看到
But regardless of where they're seen...
持续的时间有多长 表现得有多剧烈
how long their duration, or intense their display...
极光通常都表现为闪亮的帷幕
auroras usually appear as glowing curtains...
具有变幻不断的折叠和条纹
with folds or striations that change constantly.
慢镜头摄影加速了其效果
Time-lapse photography speeds up the effect.
这些明显的特征平添了极光的美丽与神秘
These signature features add to the aurora's beauty and mystery.
极光的帷幕形状
The shape of the curtains of the aurora...
其形状里的活动
and the motion within these shapes--
这些射线 缠绕 摆动 盘旋 所有这些
these rays and curls and wiggles and spirals and all of that--
是一个活生生的研究课题
is a subject of active research.
然而我们真的不了解这一切
We don't really understand all of that yet.
平添几分神秘
Adding to its mystery...
据称极光不仅能看到
are reports that the aurora can not only be seen...
而且还能听到
but also heard.
极光发生在100 或60英里的高空
The aurora is at 100 or 60-mile altitude...
声音需要用几分钟时间传过来
and the sound would take several minutes to come to us...
这样我们才能够听到它
before we can hear it.
然而人们报告说他们听到了声音
And yet people report that they hear the sound...
是与看到极光同一时刻
simultaneously when they see the aurora.
因此必定有着某种未知的机制
So there must be some unknown mechanism...
让人们认为他们听到了
that makes people think they hear...
或让他们听到了某种可能与极光相关的东西
or makes them hear something that may be associated with aurora.
对此无人能予解释
Nobody has an explanation for that...
有人正试图搞清楚其中的究竟
and some people are trying to find out what it is.
极光本身不会对人类有任何威胁
Auroras, by themselves, pose no threat to humans.
但是与之关联的太阳活动的增强
But the increased solar activity associated with them...
会产生100万兆瓦的电力
can generate about one million megawatts of electricity...
给我们带来其它方面的问题
and cause us problems in other ways...
诸如输电线路的故障
such as disruptions with power lines.
并非极光本身
It's not the aurora itself...
造成了输电线路的问题
that's causing the problem with the power lines.
而是来自太阳的带电粒子
It's the c arged particles that have come in from the Sun...
造成了危害
and they cause the damage...
干扰了输电线路
and the interference to the power lines.
那是一个要搞清的重要区别
That's an important distinction to make.
随着带电粒子...
With that increased activity and movement...
活跃于运动的增强引发了极光...
of electrically charged particles that give rise to aurorae...
同时也和与电或磁场有关的...
they also interact with anything else...
其他东西相互作用
that has an electric or magnetic field associated with it.
因此那些带电粒子干扰着
So those charged particles are disrupting...
输电线路 电子器件 卫星
whether it's power lines or electronics and satellites...
手机覆盖等等之类
or cell phone coverage...
所有需要电和磁场的东西
anything where you need electric and magnetic fields...
让你的设备...
to run your apparatus will get disrupted...
在极光发生的同时发生故障
at the same time the aurorae are taking place.
这样 你收音机里有静电 电视屏幕上有杂波
So the static on your radio, the blip on your TV screen...
手机通讯中断
that dropped cell phone call...
甚至停电
or even a blackout...
如1989年打击加拿大魁北克那一次
like the one that hit Quebec, Canada, in 1989...
就是直截了当提醒了
could just be blunt reminders...
地球只是太阳系里一个平庸之地
of the Earth's humble place in the solar system.
地球只是围绕太阳的一颗行星
The Earth is just a planet going around the Sun...
太阳的大气圈远远超过地球
and the Sun has an atmosphere that extends well beyond the Earth.
因此地球实际上是生活在太阳的外层大气里
So the Earth is actually living in the outer atmosphere of the Sun.
太阳的一举一动 当它的外层大气发生变化时
What the Sun does, when it varies the outer atmosphere...
就会影响到地球
it affects the Earth.
因此它影响到系统
So it affects the systems...
我们所依赖的技术系统
the technological systems that we depend on.
尽管极光只是...
Though auroras are a mere side effect...
太阳与地球互动的副作用
of the Sun's interaction with the Earth...
但是它们可以启发我们对宇宙的认识
they can enlighten us about the cosmos.
极光是个很好的指示 有关大气层上部的情况
The aurora is a good indicator of how the upper atmosphere...
以及地球磁场与最终来自太阳的...
and the magnetic field of the Earth interact with the solar wind...
太阳风的相互作用
which eventually comes from the Sun.
因此我们可以将极光作为研究对象 本质上
So we can use the aurora as a study object, essentially...
大自然让我们去更好地了解
that nature provides for us to understand better...
宇宙其它地方所发生的情况
what goes on in the rest of the universe.
极光是太阳活动的度量之一
The auroras are one of the measures of solar activity.
因此在历史的回顾中
So in tracing history back from the present day...
追溯到10世纪 或8世纪乃至更早
back to the 10th century or the 8th century or even before...
极光就是你可以用作...
the auroras are one thing that you can use...
衡量太阳的活动
as a measure of solar activity.
太阳有个22年的活动周期
So the Sun has a 22-year cycle of activity.
每11年 它会变得比较活跃
Every 11 years, it becomes more active...
而且它还颠倒了极性 颠了个倒
and then it reverses its polarity and comes back.
然而你可以通过时间来追溯
But you can trace this back in time...
极光就是那最好的标志
and the auroras are one of the best markers of that.
虽然极光最常见到是在极地
While auroras are most often viewed in the polar regions...
但是其它闪亮耀眼的宇宙现象
there are other dazzling cosmic phenomena...
是所有地方都能见到的
that can be seen anywhere.
它们叫做流星
They're called shooting stars.
我们看到的流星
When we see shooting stars...
看上去好像恒星落向了地球
they look like stars that fell onto the planet Earth.
但不是那回事
But that can't be right.
恒星比地球大多了
Stars are much bigger than the planet Earth.
如果你真的看到有一颗流星
If you really had a shooting star...
那它会在一秒钟内吞噬掉地球
it would gobble up the Earth within a fraction of a second.
因此如果它不是恒星 那又是什么呢?
So if it's not a star, then what is it?
那只是个小石子
It's just a little, tiny pebble...
比如来自外太空的一粒沙子
like a grain of sand from outer space...
划过我们的大气层
zipping through our atmosphere...
与大气里的分子和原子相撞
and colliding with the molecules and atoms in the atmosphere...
引起它们发光
and causing them to glow.
所以它根本不是恒星
So it's not a star at all...
与恒星风马牛不相及
nothing even remotely similar to a star.
这些闪闪发光的石子就是大家熟知的流星
These glowing pebbles are better known as meteors.
大多数在焚毁在大气层
Most burn up in the atmosphere.
有些 如果它们足够大的花
Some, if they're large enough...
就可以让它一路穿过大气层
can make it all the way through the atmosphere...
落到地球上
and drop to the Earth...
我们就会发现叫做陨石的石头
and we find a rock called a meteorite.
那其实是同一类现象
And that is really the same phenomenon.
构成流星的石头和尘埃粒子
The pebbles and dust particles that make up meteors...
是我们太阳系形成时残留的
are leftovers from the formation of our solar system...
主要是前几代恒星的碎片
mostly scattered debris from previous generations of stars.
其中许多还是来自小行星带
Many of them also come from the asteroid belt.
在火星与木星之间
Between Mars and Jupiter...
有一大堆石块漂浮在那里
there's a whole bunch of rocks floating around.
偶尔 它们会互相撞击 破碎
And, occasionally, they hit each other and shatter...
这些小颗粒在太阳系里飞来飞去
and these little grains go flying around in the solar system...
其中有些最终会越过地球的大气层
and some of them eventually intersect Earth's atmosphere.
在每年的某些时候
At certain times of the year...
有大量的流星接二连三划过天空
a large number of meteors streak across the sky.
这种事件称为流星雨
These events are called meteor showers.
它们发生在地球穿过一串碎片
They occur when the Earth passes through a trail of debris...
彗星经过太阳时留下的大量冰粒与尘埃
bits of ice and grit left by a comet as it orbits the Sun.
你看到流星雨时
When you look at a meteor shower...
流星似乎是从天上某一个点散发出来
the meteors or shooting stars appear to emanate...
光芒四射
from a single point in the sky, the radiant.
它们从那里射出
They radiate away from there.
但是 实际上 形成流星的小冰粒和石子
But, really, the little bits of ice and rock...
成堆穿行...
that make up the meteors are traveling in a bundle...
基本上是平行穿越太空的
along essentially parallel paths through space.
它们并不是从一个点上散开的
They're not diverging from a single point.
它们只是表现出散开状
They only appear to be spreading apart...
因为透视的缘故
because of the perspective...
事实上 你是在远距离看它们
the fact that you're looking at them from a great distance...
它们似乎是出自消失点
and they seem to come from vanishing point.
你可以看到这个走廊里同样的情况
You can see the exact same thing in this hallway.
墙壁是相互平行的
The walls are parallel to one another...
顶棚平行于地坪
the ceiling is parallel to the floor...
墙壁与地坪之间的交线
the lines of intersection between the floor and the wall...
顶棚与墙壁的交线都是相互平行的
and the ceiling and the wall are parallel to one another...
但是它们似乎是汇聚于远处的走廊那一头
but they all appear to converge far down the hallway there.
它们都出自消失点 是因为透视的缘故
They come from a vanishing point because of the perspective.
如果你以同样的方式回到流星上去
And if you go back to the meteors...
粒子都是相互平行的
in a similar way, the particles are all traveling parallel to one another...
但是只表现出散射状
but only appear to diverge from the radiant...
那是透视的缘故
because of perspective.
流星雨以星座命名
Meteor showers are named after the constellations...
它们似乎从那里发源
from where they appear to emanate...
虽然它们与星座里的恒星...
even though they have nothing to do...
毫无关系
with the stars in the constellation.
狮子座流星雨
The Leonid meteor showers...
以狮子座命名
named after the constellation Leo...
是某些记录在案最璀璨的
are some of the most brilliant on record.
1833年的那次 有人统计到
The one in 1833, by some accounts...
每小时多达20万颗流星
had as many as 200,000 meteors per hour.
有些观众认为世界行将终结了
Some observers thought the world was coming to an end.
但是从某些方面来说 这只是个开头
But in some ways, it was just the beginning.
近年来 新的宇宙现象已经被发现
In recent years, new cosmic phenomena have been discovered...
比流星雨更加眼花缭乱
that are even more dazzling than meteor showers.
它们发出的亮丽光彩如闪电般的速度
They emit brilliant colors at lightning quick speed.
一眨眼之间 你都无法觉察 但是我们抓住了它们
Blink and you'll miss them, but we got them.
宇宙射线听上去就像是科幻电影里的东西
Cosmic rays sound like something from a sci-fi movie...
来自外太空的无形力量
an invisible force from outer space...
可以导致天气及其它的变化
that can cause changes in weather and much more.
然而宇宙射线是真实的 虽然其名字有点名不符实
But cosmic rays are real, even if the term is a misnomer.
宇宙射线是粒子
Cosmic rays are particles.
它们并不是射线
They're not rays.
他们原先以为或许
They were originally thought that maybe...
它们是光现象 但它们不是
they were a light phenomenon, but they're not.
它们是粒子
They're particles.
构成它们的元素完全等同于太阳和地球
They're made of the same elements that the Sun and Earth...
以及宇宙中所有物体的成分
and everything in the universe is made of.
宇宙射线是来自外太空的所有辐射
Cosmic rays are any radiation that comes from outer space...
因此有很多不同的来源
so there's lots of different sources.
主要的来源是太阳
The main ones are the Sun...
因为它加速了大量的高能粒子
because it accelerates a lot of energetic particles...
其它来源是恒星 星系
and the other one is stars and galaxies...
黑洞
black holes...
中子星
neutron stars...
其它一切
everything else.
多数宇宙射线按地球标准...
Most cosmic rays are not super energetic...
并不是超级强劲...
by Earth's standards...
但最强劲的会相当于
but the most energetic ones would be the equivalent...
力道强劲的网球打中你的头部
of like a well-hit tennis ball hitting you in the had.
那感觉不是滋味
That would not feel good.
但是其中许多就像是小豌豆
But many of them are like a little pea...
豌豆射手投向你
from a pea shooter impinging upon you...
甚至还没有那个力道
or even less energy than that.
地球大气层保护我们免遭大部分宇宙射线
The Earth's atmosphere protects us from most cosmic rays...
但是那些高能粒子
but those high-energy particles...
会设法穿过大气层
that do manage to penetrate the atmosphere...
强大到足以对所有的生物产生影响
are potent enough to make an impact on all living organisms.
它们可以导致DNA的突变
They can cause mutations in the DNA.
事实上 那是权威解释之一
In fact, that's one of the canonical explanations...
为什么物种间会存在着遗传偏离
for why there is a genetic drift among species...
那是因为宇宙射线造成了DNS的一点点改变
because cosmic rays cause the DNA to change a little bit...
导致了动物物种间的变异
and that leads to variations in species of animals.
其中的一些突变产生了往好的方向进化
Some of these mutations influence evolution for the better.
何为进化?
What is evolution?
它所基于的概念就是你的基因可以改变
It's based on the idea that your genes can change...
极其细微 代代相传
ever so slightly from generation to generation...
使得你更加适应地球的变化
making you more adapted to changes on the planet Earth.
由于有宇宙射线源源不断流向我们
Since there are cosmic radiations...
即使是在我们说话的当口
raining down on us even as we speak...
这就意味着我们的基因每天都在改变
it means that our genes are being altered every day...
依靠亚原子粒子的影响
by impacts from subatomic particles...
这意味着我们能够适应不断的变化
meaning that we can adapt to changing conditions...
因为宇宙射线给了我们滚动的宇宙骰子
because cosmic rays give us a cosmic roll of the dice...
来改变我们的基因构成
which changes our genetic makeup.
宇宙射线也会造成不良的突变
Cosmic rays can also cause bad mutations...
会导致癌症
that can lead to cancer.
好消息是...
The good news is that even though...
即使有每秒钟成千上万的宇宙射线
there are thousands of cosmic rays...
穿过你的身体
passing through our bodies every second...
它们太小了 乃至
they're so tiny that the likelihood...
其击中一个DNA
that they'll hit right on a spot of DNA...
干扰细胞核 引起细胞癌变的可能性...
that disrupts that nucleus and makes that cell cancerous...
非常非常的小
is very, very, very small.
但是如果你处在宇航员所面临的环境中
But if you're in an environment like the astronauts face...
你会有大量的辐射 极少的屏蔽
where you have a lot of radiation, very little shielding...
那么你就可能积累某些风险
then you can start to accumulate some risk...
受到辐射的伤害
of being hurt by the radiation.
穿越极地航班的乘客同样会存在着
Passengers on transpolar flights also may be at risk...
暴露在宇宙射线里 增加辐射的风险
of increased radiation exposure from cosmic rays.
事实上 某些穿越极地航班的...
In fact, some of the crew members...
机组成员...
on transatlantic transpolar flights...
实际上会佩上小小的辐射徽章
will actually wear little radiation badges...
他们其实是劝阻孕妇
and they actually discourage pregnant women...
别当那些特殊航班的空姐或飞行员
from being stewardesses or pilots on those particular flights...
因为他们有所担心
because they're worried about it...
他们无法证明其实际效果
and they haven't demonstrated that it's actually an effect...
但是他们非常在意那些辐射水平
but they are very careful about those ra iation levels.
宇宙射线不仅会对...
Cosmic rays not only make an impact...
所有的生物产生影响...
on all living organisms...
同时也会对天气产生许多影响
they also may influence the weather.
有些理论认为星系间的宇宙射线
There are some theories that galactic cosmic rays...
可能扮演了雷暴
may be part of the initiation of thunderstorms...
实际就是雷击的肇事者
actual lightning strikes...
因为它们可能产生电离穿通道
because they can cause an ionization path...
穿过大气层
through the atmosphere...
有可能正好打开了...
that might just open up the path that's needed...
雷击启动所需的通道
for the lightning bolt to start.
我们在下雷雨时都见过闪电
We've all seen lightning during a thunderstorm...
但是恐怖与壮观在这些闪电中并存
but as scary and spectacular as these deadly bolts can be...
它们其实是处在同时发生在大气层上部的
they're literally on the low end of related phenomena...
所谓的瞬时发光事件的低端
known as transient luminous events that take place in the upper atmosphere.
由于高速摄像机的进步
Thanks to advances in high-speed video cameras...
我们已经能够证实它们的存在了
we've been able to verify their existence.
其中之一叫做妖精
One of them is called a sprite.
这种水母状的闪光
This jellyfish-shaped flash of light...
出现在离地45英里的高空
appears about 45 miles above the Earth's surface...
只持续几微秒钟
and lasts only a few milliseconds.
妖精是一种有趣的放电
Sprites are an interesting electrical discharge...
某些情况下会高达55甚至60英里
that can go up to something like 55 or even 60 miles in some cases...
但是它也会降低高度
but it can also go down to an altitude...
到离地30英里的高度
of maybe 30 miles above the Earth's surface.
所以你就看到有两束电流
So you have these two streams of electricity...
同时上上下下
going both up and down...
它有时是红橙色
and it sometimes has a reddish-orange hue...
是激发了大气中的...
that's caused by excitation...
中性氮分子造成的
of neutral nitrogen molecules in the atmosphere.
另一个最近发现的现象是精灵
Another recently discovered phenomenon is elves.
不 它们不是臆造的民俗图腾
No, they're not imaginary figures of folklore.
相反 它是对过程很长注解的缩写
Rather, it's an acronym for a very long explanation of the process...
就是250英里直径范围内生成这些...
that generates these glowing bursts of energy...
闪亮的能量爆发
around 250 miles in diameter.
仔细听着 精灵代表了光排放
Ready? Elves stands for emissions of light...
和电磁脉冲源发出的甚低频扰动
and very low frequency perturbations from electromagnetic pulse sources.
精灵实际上就好像是妖精的亲戚
Elves are actually kind of a relative of sprites.
精灵与妖精之间的区别之一
The one difference between elves and sprites...
就是精灵实际上持续的时间更短
is that elves will actually last for even a shorter amount of time.
因此看到精灵的唯一办法
So the only way to see an elf...
就是要有非常复杂的相机
is to have a very sophisticated camera...
很可能非常偶然地捕捉到它
and it would have to probably catch it by accident.
精灵是肉眼看不到的
Elves are not visible by the naked eye...
因为其是非常短的能量脉冲
because it's such a short burst of energy.
靠近地球 存在着其它独特的排放现象
Closer to Earth, other distinctive discharges occur...
叫做蓝色喷流
known as blue jets.
蓝色喷流就发生在雷雨云的上方
Blue jets start from just above the tops of the thunderclou s...
离地约10英里的高空
at an altitude about ten miles above Earth's surface...
它们上行到...
and they go upwards to an altitude about 30 miles...
离地约30英里的高空
above the Earth's surface.
通常 它像是蓝色的锥形光喷射
And, usually, it's sort of a blue cone-like jet of light...
蓝色是由于中性和电离的氮分子
and the blue color comes from neutral and ionized nitrogen molecules...
被穿过的电流激发所致
that have been excited by this electrical current coming through.
因为是相对较新发现的现象
As relatively newly discovered phenomena...
蓝色喷流 精灵 妖精尚未完全搞明白
blue jets, elves, and sprites aren't fully understood.
它们对地球大气层造成的影响
The impact they have on the Earth's atmosphere...
还是一个深入探讨的过程
continues to be a source of ongoing speculation.
有一些理论认为
There are some theories...
它实际上有助于...
that it would actually serve to balance out...
平衡地球的电磁力...
the electromagnetic forces of the Earth...
精灵有可能关系到产生更多的臭氧
that the elves may be associated with producing more ozone.
一个接受它的很简单的办法
One very simple way to look at it...
就是大自然在不断地自我平衡
is that nature is constantly trying to balance itself out...
正因为如此
and because of that...
最终对地球上的生命是有好处的
there are eventual benefits to life on Earth.
宇宙现象不仅影响到天气
Cosmic phenomena not only affect the weather...
同时还有植物与动物
but also plants and animals.
没有它们与太阳的相互作用
Without their interactions with the Sun...
我们的生活将会陷入混乱
our lives would be thrown into chaos.
太阳活动就像是宇宙闹钟
The Sun acts like a cosmic alarm clock...
调节着我们的生活
regulating our lives.
我们用日出日落来度量我们的日子
We measure our days in sunrises and sunsets.
植物也一样
The same with plants.
从最娇弱的花朵到最高大的树木
The most delicate flower to the tallest tree...
都依赖这种宇宙力量来告诉它该做什么
relies on this cosmic force to tell it what to do.
一个很好的例子就是开花
One great example of that is flowering.
有些植物是短日照 有些植物是长日照
Some plants are short-day, some plants are long-day.
长日照植物可以感知每天日照的延长
The long-day plants can sense the lengthening of the Sun...
那发生在春天
of the day, that happens in spring.
短日照植物...
The short-day plants...
会感觉到冬季太阳的缩短...
feel the shortening of the Sun towards the winter...
所以菊花 举个例子 就是短日照植物
so chrysanthemums, for example, are short-day plants.
它们在秋天开花
They flower in the fall.
牵牛花或金盏花 这些都是长日照植物
Petunias or marigolds, those are long-day plants.
它们开花时 白昼在延长
They flower when daylight is getting longer.
这都是由于植物里的机制和化学化合物
This is all due to mechanisms and chemical compounds in the plant...
会检测到太阳出现的时候
that can detect the time that the Sun is out there.
告诉植物开花的时间
Telling plants when to flower...
只是太阳在它们生命中发挥关键作用的一个方面
is just one way the Sun plays a key role in their lives.
太阳所发挥的另一个作用
Another way is the role the Sun plays...
就是启动了所谓的光合作用的过程
in initiating a process called photosynthesis.
少了这种宇宙互动
Without this cosmic interaction...
植物将不复存在 我们也不例外
plants would die and so would we.
光合作用就像是太阳能电池
Photosynthesis is just like solar cells.
基本上 植物获取太阳能
Basically, the plant takes Sun energy...
将其转换成它用来生长的能量
and turns it into a form of energy it can use to grow.
叶绿素 叶子里的绿色素
Chlorophyll, the green pigment in leaves...
让植物吸收阳光并开始光合作用
allows plants to absorb sunlight and begin photosynthesis.
叶绿素是巨大的镁分子
Chlorophyll is a huge molecule of magnesium...
周围是较小的碳分子
surrounded by smaller molecules of carbon...
它们通通围着它
and they all kind of support it.
这个分子所做的就是摄取光能
What this molecule does is it takes light energy...
吸收它供植物使用
and absorbs it for things the plant can use.
光合作用触发了一个复杂的过程
Photosynthesis triggers a complex process...
让植物合并二氧化碳和水
that causes plants to combine...
以制造糖分
carbon dioxide and water to make sugar...
又转而用来制造淀粉 脂肪和蛋白质
which in turn is used to make starch, fats, and proteins--
我们的食物
the food we eat.
与此同时 植物释放出氧气供我们呼吸
At the same time, plants release oxygen for us to breathe.
如果光合作用停止运作 我们通通完蛋
lf photosynthesis were to quit working, we'd all be dead.
那就是底线
That's the bottom line.
那还包括动物
That includes animals.
和我们一样 它们依靠太阳来提供食物
Like us, they rely on the Sun to provide sustenance...
调节它们的生计
regulate their lives...
也许就是如何来导航它们在世上的道路
and just maybe how to navigate their way in the world.
导航在动物王国里非常普遍
Navigation is very widespread in the animal kingdom.
鲑鱼寻找自己的路
Salmon find their way...
回到沙砾河床去繁育后代
back to the gravel bed where they were hatched.
有北美驯鹿的大迁徙
There are big migrations of caribou.
有非洲食草动物的大迁徙
There are huge migrations of grazing animals in Africa.
有昆虫的迁徙
There are insects that migrate.
帝王蝴蝶 就是个例证 是一个精彩的案例
The monarch butterfly, for example, is a spectacular case...
出生在伊萨卡这里的成虫
where the adults that are born here in Ithaca...
会去墨西哥过冬
go and spend the winter down in Mexico...
然后再回来
and then come back.
有好多好多这方面的例子
There are many, many examples of this...
并非对其中的某一个 我们确实已经完全搞明白了
and not for a single one of them do we really understand fully...
它们用来长途跋涉的指示
the cues that they are using on these long journeys.
研究提供了动物导航之谜的某些线索
Studies offer some clues to the mystery of how animals navigate.
许多物种利用太阳来确定方向
Many species use the Sun to determine direction.
那是多么不容易啊 你可以想一想
That's not so easy if you think about it...
因为 为了那样利用太阳
because, in order to use the Sun that way...
你就必须要有个时钟
you have to have a clock.
也就是说 你需要知道
That is, you need to know...
究竟是上午 还是中午或下午
whether it's the morning, noon, or afternoon...
因为太阳在移动
because of the apparent movement of the Sun.
因此动物事实上具有生物钟
And so animals do, in fact, have a biological clock...
如我们一样 给它们正确的时间
as do we, which gives them the right time of day.
如果环境掩盖了太阳
If conditions obscure the Sun...
有些动物会转换到地球的磁场
some animals switch to the Earth's magnetic field...
源于地球熔岩核心的力量
a force that originates deep in the planet's molten core.
它不仅提供了方向的指向 而且还有分布线
It provides not only directional pointers, but also positioning cues.
地球上的每个地方都有独特的磁场特征
Every place on Earth has a unique magnetic signature.
如果动物充分敏感
If an animal is sufficiently sensitive...
就有可能利用地球的磁场
it may be able to use the Earth's magnetic field...
找到老巢的位置
to figure out where it is in relation to home...
依靠追踪磁场的差异
by monitoring the differences in magnetic fields.
利用地球磁场定位...
The problem with using the Earth's magnetic field...
所带来的问题...
to locate your position...
是地球的磁场会发生变化的
is that the Earth's magnetic field changes.
它昼夜变化
It changes from night to day.
它的变化源自地下的铁矿
It changes because of deposits of iron...
叫做磁异常
under the surface of the Earth called magnetic anomalies...
对其进行了扭曲
which distort it.
它同样会因为太阳黑子产生差异
And it also varies because of sunspots...
从而导致磁场的变化
which cause variation in the field.
所有这一切意味着它相对比较嘈杂
And all of these things means that it's relatively noisy...
但似乎许多动物...
and yet it seems many animals...
可以利用它来找到自己的路
are able to make use of it to find their way.
对信鸽的投放训练
A training toss of homing pigeons...
表明动物可以利用太阳
shows how animals may use the Sun...
和地球的磁场来找到归家之路的
and the Earth's magnetic field to find their way home.
信鸽经过多年的驯养
Homing pigeons have been domesticated for years...
具备了这种找到归家之路的能力
for this ability to find their way home.
它们已经世世代代凸显出
They have been raised for generations...
成为了鸽子世界的佼佼者
to be the athletes of the pigeon world.
因此它们可以长距离飞行
So they fly very long distances.
释放鸽子的第一步
The first step in a pigeon release...
是你打开你的鸽棚
is you go out to your loft...
挑选你要用的鸽子
and you select the pigeons that you're going to use...
来进行当天的投放训练
for the training toss that day.
我所观察得就是我想要确保所有的鸽子
And what I look for is I want to make sure all the pigeons...
都具有良好的身体条件
are in good physical condition...
它们的羽毛完好无损
their feathers are all in perfect condition...
它们要有跃跃欲试的样子
and they look like they want to fly.
我会挑选这些鸽子
And I'll select those pigeons...
把它们放到鸽笼里
and I'll put them in what is called a pigeon basket...
基本上是一只小盒子
which is basically a small box...
用来运送鸽子
that is used to transport the pigeons...
从它们的鸽棚送到释放点
from their home loft over to the release point.
鸽子投放的下一步就是实际释放
The next step in the pigeon toss is the actual release...
我们来到野外
where we come out into a field...
那里四周没有树木 是一个开阔的场地
where there are no trees around, and it's an open area,
我们打开笼子 放鸽子出去
and we open the box and let the pigeons go.
一旦飞向蓝天 鸽子们 专家认为
Once in flight, the pigeons, experts think...
首先是利用太阳来定位自己
first use the Sun to orient themselves...
然后导航归家的路
then navigate their way home...
或许会利用它们的嗅觉...
probably by using their sense of smell...
和地球的磁场
and the Earth's magnetic field.
有两个感官似乎是涉及了
There are two sense organs that seem to be involved...
地球磁场的侦测
in detecting the Earth's magnetic field.
一个是视觉系统 在眼睛里
One is in the visual system, in the eye...
在眼睛的视网膜里
in the retina of the eye...
另一个是在鸽子的上喙里
and the other is in the pigeon's upper beak...
鸟嘴的下部
the mandible of the beak...
那里有成堆的磁铁
where there a whole bunch of deposits of magnetite...
那是种磁性物质
which is a magnetic mineral...
那似乎也涉及到磁场的侦测
and that also seems to be involved in detecting the magnetic field.
因此存在着两个感官
So there are two sense organs...
我们仍然没有真正搞明白这些到底是如何互动的
and we still don't really understand exactly how these interact...
以及它们是如何被动物用来找路的
and how they are used by animals to find their way around.
鸽子投放的最后阶段就是返回
The last part of a pigeon toss is the return...
鸽子飞回自己的鸽棚
where the pigeons fly back to their loft...
降落在平台上 然后回到里面去
and land on the platform and then go back inside.
简单的鸽子投放可以表明 但是无法完全解释
A simple pigeon toss may show, but doesn't fully explain...
动物是如何利用宇宙来导航的
how animals use the cosmos to navigate.
这是个让人迷糊之谜
It's a confounding mystery...
可能永远都无法彻底解决的
that may never be completely solved.
动物利用多种技术
And it's made very difficult by the fact...
事实上产生了很大的困难
that animals use several different techniques.
因此 一旦你依照传统
And so, when you do the usual classical thing...
让它们很难利用太阳时
of making it hard for them to use the Sun...
它们就会转而利用地球磁场
the stinkers switch and use the Earth's magnetic field.
它们的装备中
And it's this whole business...
有着各种不同的工具的整个情形
of having a number of different tools in their armory...
宛如我们找路一般
just as we do in finding our way around...
使其非常困难实地去解决
that makes it so very difficult experimentally to unravel...
究竟是怎么回事
exactly what is going on.
和磁场一样 存在着另一股宇宙力量
Like the magnetic field, there's another cosmic force...
以神秘的方式影响着地球上的生命
that affects life on Earth in mysterious ways.
它隐藏在光天化日之下 但是没有什么躲得过它
It hides in broad daylight, but there's no hiding from it.
置其不顾 你将会被灼伤或病变
Ignore it, and you'll get burned or worse.
宇宙现象给我们带来了我们渴望的黄金海岸
A cosmic phenomenon gives us that golden tan we crave...
看上去健康的外表
and that seemingly healthy look.
但是只要看看皮肤深处
But that look only goes skin deep.
褐色是最常见的影响
A tan is the most common effect...
来自强大而致命的太阳能
from a potentially deadly solar source...
UV 即紫外线
UV or ultraviolet rays.
紫外线是光谱的一部分
Ultraviolet is that part of the spectrum...
我们的肉眼无法看到
that we can't see with our eyes...
但是存在着相当的量
but there's a fair amount of it out there...
太阳一直在源源不断地发出
and the Sun is putting it out all of the time.
现在 就像可见光谱里的各种颜色
Now, just like there are colors in the visible spectrum...
紫外线的颜色
there are colors of ultraviolet...
取决于其光波的形式
depending on what the wavelength is...
我们把它们分成三种不同的波段:
and we've divided them into three different bands:
紫外线 A B C
Ultraviolet A, B, and C.
比如 紫外线C就几乎被臭氧层...
For example, ultraviolet C is blocked almost completely...
完全阻挡了
by the ozone layer.
紫外线B能通过一点点
Ultraviolet B gets through a little bit more...
紫外线A则大部分通过
and ultraviolet A gets through the most...
因为它最接近于可见光
because it's the closest t being visible light.
UVA被认为是造成老化和皮肤癌的射线
UVA is considered the aging and skin cancer ray...
UVB被认为是烧灼的射线
and UVB is considered the burning ray.
因此UVB射线会造成灼伤
So the UVB rays cause sunburns...
UVA射线会造成雀斑和晒斑
and the UVA rays cause the freckles and the sunspots.
这是个皮肤的横断面模型
This is a model of a cross-section of skin.
当你在户外时 UVB将会进入你的皮肤表层
When you're outside, the UVB light will go superficial into the skin...
产生晒斑
and cause sunburn.
这样就会伤害到我们皮肤的细胞 角质细胞
So that will damage the cells that make up our skin, keratinocytes.
一旦细胞受到伤害
When the cells are damaged...
身体会通过激活免疫系统累响应
the body responds by activating the immune system...
会向受伤的区域增加血流量
and that will increase the blood flow to the area of injury...
于是就会激活免疫细胞
and then it will activate the immune cells...
产生小分子 引起炎症
to produce small molecules that causes inflammation.
那只是开了个头
And that's just the beginning.
长期暴露在太阳的UVB中 会导致白内障
Prolonged exposure to UVB rays from the Sun can cause cataracts...
它还会引发皮肤癌
and it can also be a factor in skin cancers...
如黑素瘤 一种潜在的致命疾病
such as melanoma, a potentially fatal disease.
日照产生的皮肤癌高风险人群
The people at most risk of developing skin cancers...
就是那些皮肤最亮的人
from sun exposure are the lightest-skinned people...
眼睛最亮的人
the people with the lightest eyes...
生活在阳光里的人
the people who live in the Sun...
从来不抹防晒霜的人
the people who never wear sunscreen.
他们最具危险
Those are the most at risk.
然而 UVB照射有其光明的一面
There is, however, a bright side to UVB exposure...
那就是在皮肤里产生维生素D
and that's the production of vitamin D in the skin.
我们可以用天生的分子来产生维生素D
We could produce vitamin D with an innate molecule...
那实际上就是在皮肤里施加UV辐射
that's actually in the skin plus UV radiation...
将这种分子转换成维生素D
which converts this molecule into vitamin D...
那是我们健康的骨骼 健康的钙代谢所必需的
which we need for healthy bones, healthy calcium metabolism.
不过我们也可以从强化食物
However, we can also get that vitamin D...
和补品中获取维生素D
from fortified foods and from supplements.
因此我们绝对不必从紫外线来获得它
So we don't absolutely have to get it from UV radiation.
在UVB与皮肤表层发生作用时
While UVB interacts with the surface layer of skin...
UVA则穿透更深处
UVA penetrates deeper...
增加了日照的新皱纹
adding a new wrinkle to sun exposure.
UVA照射深入到皮肤的下层
UVA exposure that goes deep into the lower layer of the skin...
会导致照片老化 通过增加分解胶原蛋白的
will lead to photo aging and will break the collagen...
生化酶来破坏胶原蛋白
by increasing enzymes that break up the collagen...
那是皮肤里的弹性纤维
and the elastic fibers that's in the dermis...
给我们带来年轻 紧绷 健康的皮肤
that gives us the youthful and tight and healthy skin.
日光棚试图人为再现太阳照射
Tanning booths try to recreate the Sun's rays artificially...
但是暴晒在棚子里的人造太阳下
but exposure to manmade sun in a booth...
其错误远甚于躺在9300万英里外的...
is worse than lying under the real thing...
真东西下
93 million miles away.
日光棚商家会让你觉得
The tanning booth industry will make you think...
日光棚更加安全
that tanning booths are safer...
你躺在里面所得到的褐色
and the tan you get from laying in hem...
是更为安全 更加渐进的褐色 但事实恰恰相反
is a safer, more gradual tan, but the opposite is true.
事实上 日光棚更加有害于皮肤
In fact, tanning booths are even more harmful to the skin.
其原因就在于因为灯泡超过九成是UVA射线
The reason is because the bulbs are over 90 percent UVA rays...
那些UVA射线是老化和皮肤癌射线
and those A rays are the aging and skin cancer rays...
这样人们在二 三十年后将会患上皮肤癌
so people will develop skin cancers 20 and 30 years later.
一个众所周知的事实 就是去日晒沙龙
It's a known fact that going to the tanning salon...
会增加你患皮肤癌的风险
increases your risk of skin cancer.
许多人还认为普通防晒霜
Many people also think that regular sunscreen...
将会保护他们免除皮肤癌和过早老化
will protect them from skin cancer and premature aging.
事实并非如此
Not true.
还没有一个高防晒指数(SPF)的防晒霜
Not even sunscreens with a high SPF number...
能够防止来自太阳的这些有害影响
will prevent these harmful effects from the Sun.
SPF是防晒指数
SPF is sun protection factor...
它用来测量你可以在阳光下多长时间
and it measures how much time you can be out in the Sun...
没有被灼伤
without getting burned.
因此SPF指数只是测量UVB的保护 而不是UVA
So SPF factor only measures the UVB protection, not UVA.
最有效的防晒
The most effective sunscreens...
将同时提供对UVB 和UVA两者的防护
provide protection against both UVB and UVA.
但是即使频繁的使用
But even with frequent reapplications...
防晒霜也无法保证...
sunscreens are no guarantee against skin cancer...
皮肤癌不会增加...
which may be increasing...
原因就在臭氧层的消耗
due to the depletion of the ozone layer.
臭氧的作用在于它形成了类似毯子罩住我们
What ozone does is it forms sort of a blanket over us...
吸收了大量入侵的辐射
that absorbs a lot of the incoming radiation.
因此 要是你失去了你的臭氧
So what happens, if you lose your ozone...
你就会得到越来越多的这种高能辐射 UVB
you get more and more of this higher energy radiation, the UVB...
那种危害你皮肤的坏东西
and that's the stuff that's bad for causing damage to your skin.
值得注意的是 在20亿年前
It's interesting to note that two billion years ago...
地球上为形成富氧大气之前
before the Earth had an oxygen-rich atmosphere...
还没有臭氧层
it had no ozone layer...
地球表面并不存在生命
and life did not exist on the surface of the Earth.
它只能存在于海平面下方
It could only exist under the ocean layers...
在那里它受到海水保护免受紫外线
where it's protected from ultraviolet light by the water.
虽然紫外线看不见摸不着 其影响可能会危害我们
While ultraviolet light is invisible and its effects may harm us...
可是太阳的可见光是源头
the Sun's visible light is the source...
产生了可能是所有当中最美丽的宇宙效应
of what may be the most beautiful cosmic effect of all.
太阳扮演了关键的角色
The Sun plays a key role...
产生了所有最壮观的光彩秀之一:
in causing one of the most spectacular light shows of all:
彩虹
Rainbows.
彩虹来自阳光 它就是我们所谓的白光
Rainbows form when sunlight, which we call white light...
穿过球形水珠
passes through spherical droplets--
雨滴就是最常见的球形水珠
rain is generally spherical droplets--
光被分散...
and the light gets dispersed...
或散开成多彩的彩虹...
or spread out into a rainbow of colors...
因为光通过水珠时
because the light bends by different amounts...
按照颜色或波长
as it goes through the droplet...
产生出不同的折射
depending on its color or wavelength.
红色在一端 长波长
The red is one extreme, long wavelength.
蓝色在另一端 它是短波长
The blue is another extreme, which is a short wavelength.
当然 有其他颜色
Of course, there are other colors...
当中有其它的波长
there's other wavelengths in between...
以不同的角度折射
that are refracted at different angles.
因此那就是为何你要获取光谱
So that's why you get that spectrum of light...
因为波长的改变是连续的
because the change in wavelengths is continuous...
随着你从短波长到长波长
as you go from short up to long wave.
一个很恰当的类比 彩虹可以用棱镜来创造
A very good analogy to a rainbow can be created with a prism.
太阳 作为光源
The Sun, for the light source...
而替代雨滴的 是你现在手里的棱镜
but instead of a raindrop, you now have a prism.
不同的波长以不同的角度折射
Different wavelengths are refracted at different angles.
它们被折射两次 从另一面出来
They're refracted twice, once out of each side...
于是你看到了彩虹产生了
and then you have a rainbow that is produced...
从红色一直分离到蓝色
from the separation of red all the way through blue.
各种波长的光以各种角度给折射或弯曲
Different wavelengths of light refracted or bent at different angles...
解释了为何彩虹的色彩
explains why the colors of the rainbow...
会表现出它们的有序和弧形状
appear in the order they do and in that arc-like shape.
存在着特定的一系列角度
There is a certain set angle...
绝大多数的光被弯曲了
where a preponderance of the light is bent...
因此它聚集在了那里
and so it collects up there.
存在一个特定的角度
There's a certain angle...
其中的射线要多于其它角度
where there are more rays than at other angles...
因为 按照阳光的入射角
because, depending on the angle of incidence of the sunlight...
更多的射线趋向弯曲进这个特定的方向
more rays tend to bunch up in this particular direction.
那个角度是反日点的42度
That angle is 42 degrees from the anti-solar point...
一个有趣的天文术语 表示你脑袋的阴影
a fancy astronomical term for the shadow of your head.
在那个角度上 入射光最为强烈
At that angle, the incoming light is at its most intense...
是彩虹出现之处
and where the rainbow appears.
但是你脑袋影子形成的42度
But 42 degrees from the shadow of your head...
是不同于其他人的脑袋影子...
is different than 42 degrees...
形成的42度的
from the shadow of someone else's head.
这就意味着不会有两个人看到完全一模一样的彩虹
This means no two people see the exact same rainbow.
有时 要是你真够幸运
Sometimes, if you're really lucky...
或至少站在了正确的角度
or at least standing at the right angle...
你将会看到副虹
you'll see a secondary rainbow.
雨滴里所发生的 就是你看到这种衍射
What happens inside the raindrop where you have this diffraction...
有时它会不止一次地跳动
sometimes it bounces more than once.
因此当它第二次跳动时
And so when it bounces a second time...
它会以不同的角度出现
it comes out at a different angle...
一个更大的角度
it's a larger angle.
准确说是51度
Fifty-one degrees to be exact.
它会较为暗淡
And it'll be dimmer...
因为大部分光在第一次跳动后逃逸了
because most of the light escapes after the first bounce...
但是其中有些会进入第二次跳动
but some of it goes in the second bounce.
现在有关副虹的有趣之处
Now the interesting thing about the second rainbow...
就是其颠倒了排序
is it's in the opposite order.
因此 一条彩虹一侧的红色
So the red that's on one side on one rainbow...
将会在另一条彩虹的另外一侧
will be on the opposite side on the other.
无论是单个还是双重式样
Whether in single or double form...
彩虹都不会出现在空中的固定点
a rainbow doesn't appear at a fixed point in the sky.
它的清晰可辨取决于观察者的位置
Its apparent existence depends solely on the observer's location...
以及太阳的方位
and the position of the Sun.
由此得出 彩虹可视为是一种错觉
In this light, a rainbow may be viewed as an optical illusion.
某种程度上说 彩虹是错觉
In some ways, a rainbow is an illusion.
你无法走进彩虹 接触它 触摸它
You can't walk to a rainbow and touch it or pick it up.
它始终与你保持着远距离
It always maintains its distance away from you...
因为彩虹其实只是一组光线
'cause the rainbow really just is a set of light rays...
通过一组角度进入你的眼球
coming toward your eye from a set of angles.
只要那个方向有水珠
And as long as there are droplets in those directions...
你就会看到彩虹
you will see a rainbow.
但要是你前往水珠所在的地方
But if you go to where the droplets are...
你就改变了角度 彩虹就消失了
you've changed the angle, and the rainbow disappears.
所以说确实在那个意义上 彩虹是错觉
So really, in that sense, a rainbow is an illusion.
彩虹的简单之美与复杂的科学
The rainbow's simple beauty and complex science...
使其充满了传奇
have imbued it with legend.
古希腊人认为
The ancient Greeks considered it a path...
它是自己的神祇与凡世之间的通道
between their gods and the Earth.
爱尔兰人的妖精藏金之处
The Irish leprechaun's hiding place for his pot of gold...
据说就在彩虹的尽头
is said to be at the end of a rainbow...
一个无法抵达的地方
a place impossible to reach.
印度人相信它是一张弓
And the Hindus believed it was the bow...
属于他们的雷电之神
belonging to their god of lightning and thunder.
彩虹之美丽
The beauty of a rainbow...
光合作用之复杂
the complexity of photosynthesis...
紫外线之影响
the impact of UV rays...
极光之神秘
the mystique of an aurora--
这些形形色色的宇宙现象
these diverse cosmic phenomena...
都透露着我们与宇宙之间关系的线索
all shed light on our relationship with the universe.
我们只是被动的旁观者
We are anything but passive bystanders...
冷眼观察天地之间的...
in this whole pageant of phenomena that we see...
这些现象的盛会
between Earth and space.
地球上的生命演化在这种环境中
Life on Earth evolved in this environment...
有宇宙射线 极光 闪电
of cosmic rays and aurorae and lightning...
我们所见到的各种现象
and all of the kinds of phenomena that we see...
只是我们得以进化的那种环境的组成部分
is just part of the environment in which we've evolved.
所以说它和我们难分难解
And so it is part of us, and we are part of it.
我们所见到的美丽的大气现象
The beautiful atmospheric phenomena that we see...
彩虹 极光 流星飞逝
rainbows and auroras and meteors flying by...
以及潜在的有害物体
as well as the potentially harmful things...
比如来自太阳的紫外线
like UV radiation from the Sun...
告诉我们地球并不是什么孤立的星球
show us the Earth is not just some isolated sphere...
游离于宇宙
detached from the rest of the universe.
不 我们是它的一部分
No, we're part of it...
这使得世界变得更美好
This makes the earth more beautiful